Guide to the Joseph F. Mattice Papers, 1929-1985 RL.11213
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph F. Mattice papers
1929-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mattice, Joseph F.
RL.11213
1.5 Linear Feet
The Joseph F. Mattice Papers include correspondence, photographs, newspaper clippings, photographs and ephemera pertaining to the life and professional career of Joseph F. Mattice. The bulk of the collection consists of material from his political career as mayor of Asbury Park, specifically concerning the Asbury Park riots of July 1970.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Asbury Park Riots, Correspondence, Ephemera, Photographs, Newspaper Clippings, and Audiovisual materials.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph F. Mattice (January 17, 1902-July 13,1995) was the mayor of Asbury Park, New Jersey during the riots of July 1970. Mattice was a native of Asbury Park who returned after his education at Georgetown University. He became a lawyer, was elected to the Asbury Park city council, served as district court judge, and was a Monmouth County board of elections member.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joseph F. Mattice Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016.
Collection Overview
The Joseph F. Mattice Papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and ephemera ranging from 1929-1985. The material is organized into six series: Asbury Park New Jersey Riots July 1970, Correspondence, Photographs, Ephemera, Newspaper Clippings, and Audiovisual materials. There is also one oversize folder consisting of a political flyer and two magazines. Mattice acquired the materials during his career as a student at Georgetown University, lawyer, city council member, district court judge, and Monmouth County board of elections member. Mattice was mayor of Asbury Park during the July 1970 riots. The riots lasted from July 4-10, 1970. They began in reaction to the African American community’s frustration with employment discrimination and the poor living conditions in the predominately African American West side neighborhood. The riots caused significant damage to the West Side, 167 people were arrested, and local and State police were summoned. In the end, city government and West Side residents worked together to come to a resolution. The Asbury Park July 1970 riots brought national attention to the town, which is documented via the received correspondence, clippings, and ephemera in the collection.
The later correspondence consists of personal letters and papers coupled with newspaper clippings pertaining to politics in Asbury Park and Monmouth County as a whole.
Race riots; Asbury Park (N.J.); Mayors -- New Jersey; Audiocassettes; African Americans -- New Jersey; Race relations -- United States -- 20th century; Hate Speech -- United States; Mattice, Joseph F.
- Asbury Park Riots July 1970
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material related to the July 1970 riots. The riots were sparked by the lack of employment for African Americans due to discrimination and poor living conditions on the west side of Asbury Park, a predominately African American neighborhood. All correspondence in this series is incoming. Series contains letters from supporters of segregation and hate speech. Letters expressing criticism towards the Mattice administration are prevalent. Some of the letters advise Mattice to punish the rioters, while other letters accuse Mattice of not being supportive of the African American community. In contrast, there are letters from concerned citizens fearful of the riots, and letters calling for peace. This series includes clippings and other news coverage from the riots, as well as a small assortment of letters of advice to Mayor Mattice.
  - Separatist/ hate speech (Box 1)
  - Critical letters (Box 1)
  - Letters of support (Box 1)
  - Concerned citizens (Box 1)
  - Letters of advice (Box 1)
  - News coverage (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1957-1985
  This series contains cards and congratulatory letters regarding Mattice’s election as city council member and mayor, including a letter from then New Jersey governor Richard J. Hughes. Also includes incoming correspondence from town citizens, friends, and associates of Mattice. Most of this correspondence is incoming.
  - 1957 City Council election (Box 1)
  - 1969 Mayoral election (Box 1)
  - General correspondence 1960-1985 (Box 1)
- Ephemera 1929-1987, undated
  This series contains ephemera related to a 1934 Bermuda legal case, Mattice's political career, Asbury Park politics, and assorted personal items.
  - 1934 Bermuda legal case (Box 1)
  - Political (Box 1)
  - Miscellany (Box 1)
- Photographs 1959-1973, undated
  This series consists of photographs from the Asbury Park Publicity department and unidentified sources. There is a set of photographs from the 1st annual New Jersey Mayor’s Golf Tournament which was held at the Asbury Park Golf and Country Club. Also included are headshots and professional photographs of Mattice from his educational and political career, and assorted photographs of Mattice and others at events.
  - 1st Annual New Jersey Mayor's Golf Tournament (Box 2)
  - Headshots and professional photographs (Box 2)
  - Assorted photographs (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings 1939-1977, undated
  This series consists of miscellaneous clippings from undated and unsourced newspapers. The bulk of the clippings are from or relating to Asbury Park, New Jersey and Monmouth County, New Jersey.
  - 1930s-1950s, undated (Box 2, Oversize-folder 1)
  - 1960s (Box 2, Oversize-folder 1)
  - 1970s (Box 2)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1973
  This series contains one audiocassette tape.
  - 5-17-73 Veronica Smith 001-733 BET. 5-6:30pm (Box 2, Audio-cassette RL-11213-CS-0001)